Finding aid to the Jaap Diedrick Snoek Papers CA.MS.00099
Smith College Archives
Jaap Diedrick Snoek Papers
1931-1994
1968-1993
Smith College Archives
Snoek, J. Diedrick.
CA.MS.00099
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Professor of Psychology, Smith College. Papers include professional correspondence, research files, publications and photographs that document his career as a psychologist. In addition, personal correspondence and biographical information are also available in the papers.
Biographical / Historical
Jaap Diedrick Snoek, professor of psychology at Smith College from 1962-1994, was born in Eindhoven, The Netherlands in 1931. His father was an industrial research scientist in the field of physics. His mother died shortly after his birth, and Snoek was raised by a nurse, who later married Snoek's father and became his step-mother. The Snoek family lived in Holland during World War II and the German occupation, which became a formative experience in Snoek's childhood.
Snoek studied for a year at the University of Amsterdam, from 1949-1950. His studies were interrupted when the Snoek's family moved to the United States in 1950. They settled in Cleveland, Ohio, and his father died shortly thereafter. His step-mother felt that it was important for Snoek to complete his education, so she went back to work as a nurse, providing care for elderly patients in their homes. Snoek earned his B.A. in Psychology from the Western Reserve University in 1954. He continued his studies in psychology, achieving his M.A. in Psychology from the University of Michigan in 1955. Snoek also became a naturalized citizen of the United States in that year. Also during this period of his life, Snoek married his wife Barbara. Their marriage produced two children, Eric and Martha.
During his study for the M.A. degree, Snoek began his professional career in psychology. From 1954-1956, he worked as a Teaching Assistant and Fellow in the Department of Psychology at the University of Michigan. For the next three years, Snoek served as a Research Assistant at the Research Center for Group Dynamics in Ann Arbor (1956-1959). From 1959-1962, Snoek was both the Study Director at the Institute for Social Research in Ann Arbor and a Lecturer in the Department of Psychology at the University of Michigan. Snoek earned his Ph.D. in Social Psychology from the University of Michigan in 1960.
Moving from Michigan to Massachusetts, Snoek accepted a position as assistant professor in the Smith College Department of Psychology. He was an assistant professor from his arrival in 1962 until 1969, when he was promoted to associate professor. In 1978, Snoek was made a full professor in the Department of Psychology at Smith College. He served as the head of the department from 1971-1974 and again from 1982-1984. During his career at Smith, Snoek had several opportunities to teach at other institutions of higher learning. From 1966-1967, he was a visiting assistant professor at the Graduate School of Industrial Administration at the Carnegie Institute of Technology in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Snoek had the opportunity to return to his native country during the 1987-1988 school year, when he was a visiting scholar at the University of Utrecht.
Snoek taught a wide range of courses during his career as a psychology professor, including Introductory Psychology, the Psychology of Adolescence, Social Psychology, Attitudes and Opinions, and Introductory Statistics. He also was responsible for developing the courses on Adult Development and Behavior in Organizations. His seminar courses focused on such topics as Social Change, Sex Role Development, Group Dynamics, and Gender and the Life Course.
Snoek had many other professional activities associated with Smith College and beyond the scope of this institution. He was instrumental in the first years of the Project on Women and Social Change, of which he served as co-principal investigator. He also served as a consultant for the Mary Holmes College Summer Enrichment Program and the Smith-Amherst Tutorial Program. He became a licensed psychologist in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts in 1973 and had a private practice for many years. Snoek also conducted numerous human relations training and personal growth workshops from 1969 until the present, working with such organizations as Pendle Hill, Powell House, the National Training Laboratories, the National Association for Pastoral Renewal, the Friends Conference on Religion and Psychology, and others. Snoek was also a member of such professional organizations as the American Psychological Association, the Eastern Psychological Association, the Massachusetts Psychological Association, the Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, the Society for Values in Higher Education, and the Society of the Sigma Xi.
Some of Snoek's publications include "Some Effects of Rejection upon Attraction to a Group" in the Journal of Abnormal Social Psychology (1962); "Attraction in Relationships: A New Look at Interpersonal Attraction" with G. Levinger (1972); "Self-disclosure among Adolescents in Relation to Parental Control and Affection" with Dr. Esther Rothblum, Smith class of 1976, in Adolescence (1979); and "Mara: The Construction of a Professional Identity" in the book Women Living Change (1985).
Scope and Contents
The Snoek Papers contain professional correspondence, research files, publications and photographs that document his career as a psychologist at Smith College between 1962-1994. In addition, personal correspondence and biographical information are also available in the papers.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical and Personal Material
II. Correspondence
III. Professional Activities
IV. Speaking and Writing
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated by Professor Snoek in 1996.
Psychology--Study and teaching (Higher)--Massachusetts --Northampton.; Snoek, J. Diedrick.; Smith College--Faculty.; Conway, Jill Ker; Dunn, Mary Maples.; Pettigrew, Thomas F.; Snoek, J. Diedrick.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND PERSONAL MATERIAL, 1931-1994; undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a curriculum vitae, description of current research interests, newspaper clippings, letters to editor of the Daily Hampshire Gazette, and photographs.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1023.1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1023.1, Folder 2)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1966-1992; undated
  This series consists of personal and professional correspondence with Smith presidents, colleagues and friends, organizations, and publishers. The letters are arranged according to the name of the correspondent or organization. Snoek's outgoing correspondence, if extant, is filed chronologically with the correspondence which he received it.
  - General, 1966-1984 (Box 1023.1, Folder 3)
  - Conway, Jill Kerr, 1982 (Box 1023.1, Folder 4)
  - Dunn, Mary Maples, 1986-1992 (Box 1023.1, Folder 5)
  - Gibb, Jack R., 1972 (Box 1023.1, Folder 6)
  - Global Survival Studies at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst, 1972-1973 (Box 1023.1, Folder 7)
  - Massachusetts Psychological Association, 1982 (Box 1023.1, Folder 8)
  - The Women's Center of the National Council of Negro Women, 1981-1982 (Box 1023.1, Folder 9)
  - Pendle Hill, 1972-1980 (Box 1023.1, Folder 10)
  - Pettigrew, Thomas F., 1985 (Box 1023.1, Folder 11)
  - Rabbie, Jacob, 1985-1987 (Box 1023.1, Folder 12)
  - Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society, 1981-1982 (Box 1023.1, Folder 13)
  - Yale University Press, 1986 (Box 1023.1, Folder 14)
- Series III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, 1968-1994
  This series is divided into two sections: Smith and Beyond Smith.
  Professional activities at Smith consists of collaborative work with Smith students, including their personal and professional correspondence with Snoek; new course proposals; consulting work for the Mary Holmes College Summer Enrichment Program and the Smith-Amherst Tutorial Program; course materials for Smith psychology classes; and the Project on Women and Social Change. They are arranged alphabetically.
  Professional activities Beyond Smith include personal growth workshops at Powell House, the National Association for Pastoral Renewal, and others; and the Society for Values in Higher Education. They are arranged alphabetically.
  - Smith
    - Collaborative Work
      - Delores Mei '77, 1977-78 (Box 1023.1, Folder 15)
      - Esther Rothblum '76, 1976-1986 (Box 1023.1, Folder 16)
    - Committee on Educational Policy: New Course on Teaching in the Urban Ghetto, 1968 (Box 1023.1, Folder 17)
    - Consultant Work
      - Mary Holmes College Summer Enrichment Program, Mississippi, 1968 (Box 1023.1, Folder 18)
      - Smith-Amherst Tutorial Program, 1969 (Box 1023.1, Folder 19)
    - Project on Women and Social Change
      - General, 1978-1984; undated (Box 1023.1, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1987 (Box 1023.1, Folder 21)
    - Proposal for Course on Aging, 1987 (Box 1023.1, Folder 22)
    - Courses Materials
      - Psychology 243: Adult Development and Aging, Spring 1994 (Box 1023.1, Folder 23)
      - Psychology 278: Behavior in Organizations, Spring1994 (Box 1023.1, Folder 24)
      - Psychology 340: Gender and the Life Course, Spring 1994 (Box 1023.1, Folder 25)
  - Beyond Smith
    - Personal Growth Workshops
      - "Exploration of Human Potential" Retreat with Friends of the Rochester, NY Meeting, 1969-1971 (Box 1023.2, Folder 26)
      - National Association for Pastoral Renewal Retreat:, 1969 (Box 1023.2, Folder 27)
      - "An Exploration of Human Potentials" (Box 1023.2)
      - Powell House
        - General, 1970-1973; undated (Box 1023.2, Folder 28)
        - Correspondence, 1971-1974; undated (Box 1023.2, Folder 29)
    - The Society for Values in Higher Education, 1983-1988 (Box 1023.2, Folder 30)
- Series IV. SPEAKING AND WRITING, 1987-1993; undated
  This series consists primarily of texts of lectures, the lectures' accompanying graphics, psychological studies, journal articles, and book chapters. All materials in this series are arranged chronologically.
  Speaking consists of lectures at academic institutions, professional conferences, and meetings of professional associations. Writing consists of published psychological studies, journal articles, and chapters for books.
  - Lectures, 1972-1993; undated (Box 1023.2, Folder 31)
  - Publications, 1962-1987 (Box 1023.2, Folder 32)
  - Draft and Publication of "The Wounded Surgeon", 1971-1973 (Box 1023.2, Folder 33)